<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Random Apple]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.randomapple.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.randomapple.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-24T00:53:26-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.randomapple.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Michael Wilson]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[eternalprogrammer@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Advertising Models]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.randomapple.com/blog/advertising-models/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-23T16:06:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.randomapple.com/blog/advertising-models</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In today&#8217;s age, the idea that a business can offer a product for a reduced price by subsidizing the cost with advertisements is quite prevalent. But where did this business model originate?</p>

<p>It turns out the first large-scale use of this business model was introduced by <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benjamin_Day_(publisher)">Benjamin Day</a> with the introduction of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penny_press">penny press</a>.<sup><a href="#fn-1" id="fnref-1">1</a></sup> He reduced the cost of a newspaper from 6 cents to a penny, and printed at the top of every page, &#8220;The object of this paper is to lay before the public, at a price within the means of every one, all the news of the day, and at the same time offer an advantageous medium for advertisements.&#8221; This resulted in quite a remarkable change in the distribution of information, and has sustained newspapers successfully for many decades.</p>

<p>One important drawback when relying on advertising is that it inevitably decreases during a recession. This most recent recession saw a 50% cut in ad revenue for newspapers, and because of the prevalence of online display advertising, it seems that this model will never recover.</p>

<p>Now let&#8217;s look at online advertising models. Initially, a successful online ad was measured in pageviews, mirroring the print advertising model. There have been some improvements in terms of analytics, but from my perspective online advertising has not yet significantly changed the efficacy of advertising. It has simply reduced the cost of an advertisement without significantly increasing the volume, which is why it has been so detrimental to publishers relying on a percentage of the adspend.</p>

<p>I argue that as the economy recovers, we will see a growing gap between the amount of money an advertiser was spending on traditional print ads and the amount of money spent on online display ads. This will leave a large margin (almost 50%) for experimental adspend. We have already seen this with the widely available Groupon campaigns.</p>

<p>This new advertising model is still very much up for grabs, but I believe the winner will utilize all the new data being collected about the consumer, and pair them better than ever with advertisers. With the ubiquity of mobile devices, I don&#8217;t believe display advertising is going to be viable for much longer, even digitally.</p>

<p>So what is the solution? I&#8217;ve just mentioned that there will be a large surplus
of adspend in near future &#8211; so why not spend it directly on the consumer? I believe that the best utilization of this surplus is to offer FREE goods and services to consumers for both customer acquisition and retention. The company that can most effectively distribute these goods and services will steal the online ad market from today&#8217;s players. This means predicting the cost of a acquision for individual customers, their cost of retention, and their ability to bring new customers on board through word of mouth. This is a tall order, and will require the joint effort of people from many disparate disciplines. Groupon very nearly had the right idea, but unfortunately they were missing the biggest piece of the puzzle &#8211; proper targeting.</p>

<p>What this means for the newspapers is that the adspend is not coming back. They will need to find a way to distribute their content more efficiently than ever before.</p>

<p><sup id="fn-1">1</sup><sub>Some credit should be awarded to Horatio David Shepard for envisioning a penny press, but it was Benjamin Day who ultimately commercialized it successfully with advertisement. Shepard&#8217;s penny press failed within 3 weeks because it simply relied upon economies of scale. <a href="#fnref-1"> &#8617;</a></sub></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Letting Go of an Idea]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.randomapple.com/blog/letting-go-of-an-idea/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-26T12:08:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.randomapple.com/blog/letting-go-of-an-idea</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had lived in Los Angeles my whole life, and I
had always yearned to go to Silicon Valley, which I envisioned as a mecca
bustling with entrepreneurs inventing the future and investors tuning out
overly-enthusiastic elevator pitches. So earlier this year I bookmarked the
<a href="http://steveblank.com/visitors-guide/">Hacker&#8217;s Guide to Silicon Valley</a>
on my phone, rented a room in the heart of the mission district in San Francisco,
and set out on a mission to change the world with my new idea.</p>

<p>I got the sense that all of the startup action was taking
place in SOMA, so I rented an office in a coworking space there. I
saw that there was a <a href="http://www.hackersandfounders.com/">Hackers and Founders</a>
meeting in the evening, and I was incredibly excited to meet my future
cofounder. I quickly realized that even though everybody WAS looking for a cofounder,
everyone already had an idea they wanted to work on. Nobody wanted a cofounder
who already had an idea.</p>

<p>So I pressed on, determined to have my idea see the light of day one way or
another.</p>

<p>After a couple weeks of networking I started to develop a secret wish that I would
run into someone working on exactly the same idea, and that we would make a
perfect team. But as an unconnected valley outsider, the odds of this happening
to me were basically 0. I had to convince someone.</p>

<p>After a couple of <strong>months</strong> of networking, I started to feel mental
anguish. Constantly pitching my idea to other people started to feel
laborious. I began to feel like one of those crazy inventors peddling some
useless junk. And all of the buzz about the upcoming Facebook IPO made me
wonder if I could just do it all alone, like the portrayal of Mark Zuckerberg
in The Social Network.</p>

<p>People say that entrepreneurs never give up, that they exercise great mental
willpower to continue, and then eventually succeeded. The notion of a single
person facing insurmountable odds is romanticised by Hollywood, and I&#8217;m sure
everyone identifies with them at some point. But this is unrealistic. Nobody
should expect to be able to figure out an end-to-end business model all by
themselves. And having a great team to ideate with and share the burden is way
more important than whatever idea you&#8217;re currently working on. You need be
flexible, and find partners who are flexible. And it&#8217;s way faster to convince
everyone else in the valley your idea is solid with social proof than building
and marketing an MVP all by yourself.</p>

<p>Oh, and losing a cofounder starts the entire process all over again.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Get Domain Knowledge]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.randomapple.com/blog/get-domain-knowledge/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-25T20:37:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.randomapple.com/blog/get-domain-knowledge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I started feeling the itch to strike out on my own the in summer of 2011. I was
working as a software engineer, and my roommate was an excellent product manager.
<a href="http://ycombinator.com/">YCombinator</a> was getting tons of attention, especially
with the <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2011/01/28/yuri-milner-sv-angel-offer-every-new-y-combinator-startup-150k/">$150k deal</a>.</p>

<p>We thought, &#8220;Hey, we make a perfect team! Let&#8217;s come up with an idea
and apply to YC W12. If we get accepted, we&#8217;ll quit our jobs&#8221;.</p>

<p>So we spent weeks thinking really hard about how to solve the world&#8217;s problems,
how to solve our own problems, how to address the <a href="http://ycombinator.com/rfs.html">RFSs</a>.
We ended up figuring out a real problem that needed solving, a problem we also had,
and a plausible way of solving that problem. However, we got rejected and that ultimately killed
the partnership.</p>

<p>Like I&#8217;ve mentioned before, failure makes you perform a thorough examination of
what went wrong. Obviously, we hardly started so there were lot of things we were
missing. But I think the primary reason was that we underestimated how important
it was to have an extensive understanding of the domain in which our company would operate.</p>

<p>If the time is really ripe for your company, there should be a long list of
companies that have already tried and failed to do every possible variation
of your idea. I have found that <a href="http://www.crunchbase.com/">Crunchbase</a> and
<a href="http://quora.com/">Quora</a> are excellent places to find deadpooled companies and
learn why solving the problem is so difficult. It is with this knowledge that you&#8217;ll
be able to come up with a really excellent idea. One that will survive many
rejection emails, and drive the founders to press on anyways.</p>

<p>And getting this understanding takes a <strong>long time</strong>. Lots and lots of <strong>research</strong>
and <strong>asking people</strong> about your company&#8217;s domain.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[If Your Startup Fails, You'll Learn More]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.randomapple.com/blog/if-your-startup-fails/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-14T04:34:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.randomapple.com/blog/if-your-startup-fails</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was talking to my friend the other day, and we both agreed that if we had
to decide between hiring an employee who has worked at a wildly successful
company, or one that failed, we would choose the one that worked at the company
that failed.</p>

<p>Depending on the amount of funding, companies that fail can make a lot of mistakes.
And most companies do fail, so this is probably the greatest upside to working at a
startup that doesn&#8217;t make it. It&#8217;s unlikely anyone will realize what the mistakes are
at the time, but the benefit comes from hindsight. Employees at a company that fails
have likely spent years of their lives helping to build a product that ultimately will
not provide any value to society, so they naturally spend a lot of time analyzing every
decision the company made.</p>

<p>And this is why it&#8217;s great to work at a company that failed. There are so many reasons
why a company might fail, and it&#8217;s a valuable thing to have many different perspectives
on how to avoid failure inside future companies.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.randomapple.com/blog/introduction/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-28T16:17:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.randomapple.com/blog/introduction</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have decided to finally start a blog. It&#8217;s taken me a while, mostly because
I always have a hard time reading other people&#8217;s <a href="http://blogsofnote.blogspot.com">out</a>-<a href="http://wordpress.com">of</a>-<a href="http://livejournal.com">the</a>-<a href="http://tumblr.com">box</a> blogs. The designs are too
busy. I wanted something clean, something I could customize, something free.
I finally found it.</p>

<p>This blog is hosted at <a href="http://pages.github.com">Github Pages</a>, using the built-in
support for <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki">Jekyll</a>
and an added <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a> layer.</p>

<p>The hardest part is out of the way, so let me set out the purpose of this blog.
When I started college, I knew nothing about tech. I didn&#8217;t know about linux
distributions or git or current trends, and I didn&#8217;t know how to find out.
Even after graduating, I still knew nothing and only landed my first fulltime
job 10 months after graduating. Luckily, I became employee #20 at a startup
in Santa Monica, and it changed everything. Working there was one of the best
experiences of my life, and taught me so many things. So this blog is about my
experiences in the world of tech startups.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
